So, today's דף Daf is פ"ה, Peh-Heh, 85. We pick up at
the bottom of פ"ד עמוד ב' Peh-Dalet Amud Bet and we're dealing
with the middle of this whole story about רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון
Rabbi Elazar b. Rabbi Shimon who was first involved as being this
magistrate and catching גנבים Gannavim and the rabbis were not happy with
that, but and he himself was concerned that one thing he did
was rash and maybe he made a mistake although he was reassured
that it wasn't. Anyway, and then he accepted afflictions on himself, boils
and so on every night. His wife initially separated from him because
he was doing this to himself. And then when it came and
then when he died, he said, "Don't bury me right away. The
rabbis won't treat my body properly, probably because they're upset about this
whole case about being the magistrate." So he was left to lay
in the upper chamber for between 18 and 22 years until and
nothing happened to his body, it was totally preserved until it became
time to bury him. So now the גמרא, Gemara, and then he
was brought to the cave where his father was. His father was
רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai and there was a
serpent protecting the cave and they said, "Open up so that the
father can receive the son," and the serpent opened up its mouth
and let him come in. Okay, so that was the, that quick
review of just the last story we did yesterday. And now the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
So רבי Rabbi wanted to, maybe we'll pick up with there, from
a little,
we'll go back a little bit and where it says like this,
it says
שלח רבי לדבר באשתו. Shelach Rabbi ledaber be'ishto. So about 20 lines
from the bottom lines starts with פתחי פיך ויכנס. Pitchee peecha ve-ikanes.
Okay, so the middle towards the end of that line, שלח רבי
לדבר באשתו. Shelach Rabbi ledaber be'ishto. So after he died, רבי Rabbi
went to like read a שידוך shidduch with his wife, wanted to
suggest that he marry his wife. שלח רבי לדבר באשתו. Shelach Rabbi
ledaber be'ishto. This was of course the נשיא, Nasi, right, the Exilarch
of the people. שלחה ליה, Shalcha leh, she said to him, כלי
שנשתמש בו קודש ישתמש בו חול? Klee shenishtamesh bo kodesh yishtamesh bo
chol? A vessel that was used, referring to herself as a vessel,
for something holy should be used for something profane? Meaning my husband
was so holy compared to you. תמן אמרינן, Taman amrinan, and in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael this saying is, אתרא דמרי ביתא תלא זייניה,
Atra demari baita tala zaineh, in a place where the owner of
the house hangs up his weapons on that peg, כוזבא דרעיא כוזתיה
תלא? Kuzba d'raiia kuzteh tala? Do you think that the shepherd can
hang up his pouch on that same peg? שלח לה, Shelach lah,
he sent to her, נהי דבתורה גדול ממני אבל במעשים טובים מי
גדול ממני? Nehi d'veTorah gadol mimeni aval bemaasim tovim mi gadol mimeni?
I accept that maybe he was greater than me in תורה, Torah,
but since when was he greater than me in מעשים טובים? Maasim
tovim? I'm the נשיא, Nasi, I provide for the whole people.
שלחה ליה, Shalcha leh, she sent back to him, בתורה מי גדול
ממך לא ידענא. BeTorah mi gadol mimcha lo yadana. Regarding תורה Torah
that he's greater than you, that I didn't know. But you yourself
admitted it. במעשים ידענא, Bemaasim yadana, but I know when it comes
to actually good deeds that he is greater than you, דקביליה
יסורי. De-akiba lei yissurei. He accepted upon himself יסורים. Yissurim. Now I
don't
know, רבי Rabbi was upset about it. B, I don't know how
that's מעשים טובים. Maasim tovim. I mean, it sort of maybe if
you want to say it's like his personal like, you know, his
צדקות, Tzidkus, he's like his piety, it's one thing. But מעשים טובים
Maasim tovim you think have to do with how you're helping other
people. And actually it was preventing him from going to the בית
מדרש Beit Midrash and so on. So it's an interesting response. Anyway,
I don't know, there's too much גמרא Gemara here so we got
to read. So this is what it says, so here it says
when we, when she said when he would invite the suffering upon
himself each night, he would say, "May all the pains of the
Jewish people come." Oh, okay, well that's not in our story but
maybe. All right. ובתורה מאי היא? UveTorah mai hee? Now what, where
did you know, how did רבי Rabbi know he was greater than
him in תורה? Torah? דכי הוי יתבי רבן שמעון בן גמליאל ורבי
יהושע בן קרחה אספסלי. De-chi havay yasvay Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel ve-Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Korcha a-safsilei. When רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel and רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha
were sitting on the stools at the and you know, ויתבי קמייהו
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון ורבי Ve-yasvay kamaiehu Rabbi Elazar b. Rabbi Shimon
ve-Rabbi in the בית מדרש Beit Midrash and they were the teachers
or they were the advanced students and ויתבי קמייהו, Ve-yasvay kamaiehu, sat
in front of them, sounds like they were teachers sitting in front
of them was
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b. Rabbi Shimon and רבי. Rabbi.
That was when רבי Rabbi still wasn't yet רבי, Rabbi, he was
still, you know, יהודה, Yehuda, רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, whatever, his father
was, you know, the נשיא. Nasi.
ויתבי אארעא. Ve-yasvay a-ara. And they were sitting
on the ground. מקשו ומפרקו. Makshu u'mfarku. So and when they and
these the students who were sitting on the ground asked difficult questions
and answered them and clearly were showing that they were their equals
if not greater than those that were sitting on the stools, that
those were the teachers, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
and רבי יהושע בן קרחה. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha. אמרי ממימיהם אנו
שותים והם יושבים על גבי קרקע? Amri mei-meihem anu shotim ve-hem yoshvim
al gabei karka? We're drinking from their waters and they're the ones
sitting on the ground? עבדו להו ספסלי, Avdu lehu safsilei, they made
for them stools. אסקינהו, Askinhu, and they like lifted them up and
now you became the, you know, were placed in equal equal footing.
אמר ליה רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Amar leh Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel,
so רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
said to them, פרידה אחת יש לי ביניכם, Pireda achas yesh li
beinechem, because רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel was רבי'ס
Rabbi's father. So he said, "I have one like dove among you
among you." ואתם מבקשים לאבדה ממני? Ve-atem mevakshim le-avda mimeni? You and
you want to make make him lost to me? So you might
remember the whole thing about "I have one dove among you" was
also the line that according to the earlier story, one version of
the earlier story, רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai appeared
in a dream and said, "My dove, my son, is there and
he's lying, you know, hasn't been buried and he should be coming
up to me in heaven." Okay, so here it's being echoed here.
"My what, what was the problem?" that he wasn't being buried there.
No no the dove so here the problem is רש"י Rashi says
is a problem of עין הרע Ayin Hara that here the eye
is these young kids and you're going to make them treat them
as if they're like teachers or whatever you're going to welcome the
עין הרע Ayin Hara and the jealousy and that's going to you
know cause them to lose things here, right exactly who are these
punks what are they doing up there whatever so no no it's
not good for the עין הרע. Ayin Hara. So אחתוהו
לרבי, Achasunu Rebbi, so they put רבי Rebbi back down. That was
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל's Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel son. They didn't want
there to be an עין הרע Ayin Hara for רבי Rebbi so
they put him back on the floor. אמר רבי יהושע בן קרחה,
Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha, רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Korcha said: מי שיש לו אב יחיה מי שאין לו אב ימות?
mi she-yesh lo av yichye mi she-ein lo av yamut?
So what only רבי Rebbi gets the special treatment of being demoted,
the protection of being demoted? So the person who has פרוטקציה proteksia
has a father, he's the one that lives, the person who doesn't
have a father, I guess רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar
Yochai had died, he should he should die? We should expose him
to the עין הרע? Ayin Hara? So אחתוהו נמי לרבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון. achasunu nami le-Rabbi Elazar be-Rabbi Shimon.
So they also put רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar be-Rabbi Shimon
down. Okay. חלש דעתיה. Chalash daatei.
So he got so רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Rabbi Elazar be-Rabbi Shimon,
you know, was despondent. Okay why was he despondent because it sort
of you remember the חלש דעתיה chalash daatei before of רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, similar issues, asking questions, challenging,
just like echoed themes. Anyway he got despondent because he said what
are they doing? I deserve to be up on a stool. Like
maybe he didn't care about their עין הרע, Ayin Hara, right? What
are you doing? You're putting me down. And you're putting you're putting
me down because you thought you had to pull רבי Rebbi down,
so I'm being pulled down because of רבי. Rebbi. So אמר כחשיבתו
ליה כוותי, amar kachashivtu lei kavasis, you think that he's my equal,
like if he goes down I should go down. Okay. So you
know and he knew that he was his better when it comes
to תורה. Torah. So עד הוא יומא ad hu yoma until this
point he didn't make anything of it, but now you know that
this sort of like you know that they're treating him as a
result of how they treated רבי, Rebbi, like what? You're putting me
in the same category? So עד הוא יומא כי הוי אמרי רבי
מילתא הוי מסייע ליה רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. ad hu yoma ki
havay amrei Rebbi milta havay mesayei lei Rabbi Elazar be-Rabbi Shimon. Until
that point whatever רבי Rebbi would say something, רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון
Rabbi Elazar be-Rabbi Shimon would come and back him up. Right, רבי
Rebbi would be on the ground and he'd be asking some questions
of the teachers and רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar be-Rabbi Shimon
would say yes and here's you know and he'd he would back
up the question. מכאן ואילך Mikan ve-ilech from that moment on כי
הוי אמר רבי יש לי להשיב, ki havay amar Rebbi yesh li
le-hashiv, when רבי Rebbi there was sitting on the ground and the
teacher would say something and רבי Rebbi says wait I have you
know I have a question I have a response to this, אמר
ליה רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון amar lei Rabbi Elazar be-Rabbi Shimon so
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar be-Rabbi Shimon who was sitting on
the ground next to רבי Rebbi said: כך וכך יש לך להשיב?
kach ve-kach yesh lach le-hashiv? What you think that's a question? So
זו היא תשובתך? zu hi teshuvatcha? What a silly question? Here's the
answer to it. השתא הכפיננו תשובות חבילות שאין בהם ממש Hashta hikfitinu
teshuvot chavilot she-ein bahem mamash and
and you are now like surrounding us with responses you know what
are you doing wasting class time you're asking all these questions these
silly vacuous questions what type of stupid question is this? This is
the answer. Okay so he would constantly be working to undermine him.
Now it's interesting again because it echoes the רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish story where רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said he
didn't want somebody to just be his yes man and back him
up. But of course what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan wanted was a
challenge that would give him the opportunity to sharpen what he was
saying. Here you get here you get almost an the opposite. Somebody
asks a question which maybe wasn't so good and you needed somebody
else to actually help, you know sometimes a teacher sometimes a teacher
reframes a question to make it better, what I think you're asking
is the following you know. So actually here it's the opposite the
backing up was actually helping and the challenging wasn't as an opportunity
to make it better the challenging was as a way to undermine.
Okay he gets demoted I don't know you know we I appreciate
there's a lot of questions on all these but you can see
how much text we have to do. Okay so anyway
חלש דעתיה דרבי. chalash daatei de-Rebbi. So now רבי Rebbi was the
one who got despondent like you know he's being being made to
feel foolish. Anyway but it's clear for the point of the story
that רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar was smarter than him in תורה Torah
that we see. So אתא ואמר ליה לאבוה ata ve-amar lei le-avuhu
he went and he told his father רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel. אמר ליה בני אל ירע לך Amar lei beni
al yeira lecha do not let it be evil in your eyes
שהוא ארי בן ארי she-hu ari ben ari he's a lion the
son of a lion, רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai
is his father I mean come on the author of the זוהר.
Zohar. ואתה ארי בן שועל Ve-ata ari ben shual and you I'm
the son and you're ארי בן שועל ari ben shual you are
a lion but you're the son of a
fox, I רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel am not
so great in תורה, Torah, so he basically he took the insult
upon himself so that רבי Rebbi would not feel that he was
the one that was being you know insulted. Okay והיינו דאמר רבי
ve-hainu de-amar Rebbi so now we're going to switch gears that's sort
of the for the now the end of that story about רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar be-Rabbi Shimon and why his wife refused
רבי's Rebbi proposal okay and now we're going to but we're going
to now sort of move on and it's a slightly you know
whatever move on and in a slightly different focus. Yeah well רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar be-Rabbi Shimon is going to stay with
us for a while. והיינו דאמר רבי Ve-hainu de-amar Rebbi this is
what רבי Rebbi says שלשה ענוותנים הן shelosha anvesanim hen there are
three great modest people in the world who are they ואלו הן
אבא ve-eilu hen abba my father רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel ובני בתירא u-benei Beteira the בני בתירא Benei Beteira top
of פרק האשה Perek Ha-ishah ויונתן בן שאול ve-Yonatan ben Shaul and
the biblical יונתן Yonatan the son of שאול. Shaul. Now by the
way I just have to say parenthetically of course it's fascinating because
the משנה Mishnah at the end of סוטה Sotah right says that
when you know so and so happened there was no more X
in the world and when this person died there was no more
Y in the world and it says when רבי Rebbi died there
was no more ענווה anavah in the world there was no more
modesty. So here רבי... Rebbi... So here רבי Rebbe himself is saying
there are three modest people right obviously not listing himself right? Wait
a minute! I have to put myself on that list! You know,
I'm the most modest person ever! Anyway, but it's interesting that he's
listing who's modest and another source says right that רבי Rebbe was
when רבי Rebbe died, you know רבי Rebbe there was no more
modesty. Yes. Is humility and modesty the same thing? So you're right.
I mean, do you translate this as modesty as humility exactly what
ענווה Anavah is? But it's important. I mean let's see actually the
גמרא Gemara sort of explores that to a certain degree. Okay. So
we'll see what the בני בתירה Bnei Beteira are. רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel הד אמר. had amar. רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel like we said, that he basically said,
you know, I'm just a fox so it's don't take the insult
to be about you. בני בתירה, Bnei Beteira, the בני בתירה, Bnei
Beteira, דאמר מר de'amar mar
so these were בני בתירה Bnei Beteira who were sort of like
the authorities at the time of the second בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
That's clear from a number of stories. And one of them had
to do with הלל, Hillel, when they didn't know whether to bring
the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach on the שבת Shabbos when ערב פסח
Erev Pesach was שבת Shabbos and they said that they nobody knew
whether you were allowed to do it or not and somebody said,
oh, there's this guy who came from בבל Bavel and he was
משמש meshamesh שמעיה ואבטליון Shmaya ve'Avtalyon and הלל הבבלי שמו Hillel HaBavli
Shemo and הלל Hillel gave all these all these arguments about why
you could bring the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach on שבת Shabbos and
they finally accepted him. Of course, the interesting version of that story
in the תוספתא Tosefta was with that he was like he would
prove to them from a million of ways קל וחומר kal vachomer
or this or that like a million different logical arguments and it
says that they did not accept it from him. It says until
he said כך מקובלני משמעיה ואבטליון kach mekubalni mi'shmaya ve'avtalyon I have
a מסורה mesorah they said why didn't you say so in the
first place? You have a מסורה? mesorah? Which also shows about the
difference of like attitudes towards תורה שבעל פה. Torah Sheba'al Peh. How
much is it מסורה, mesorah, how much is it rationally deriving? Anyway
the upshot of that story is דאמר מר de'amar mar at the
end of that story הושיבוהו בראש, hoshivuhu barosh, they made him the
head of the you know academy and the maybe even the political
head ומינוהו לנשיא עליהם ve'innuhu l'nasi aleihem and he became the נשיא
Nasi so that was the beginning of the נשיאות nesiut from the
descendants of הלל Hillel which ultimately led to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel and to רבי Rebbe and so on. Okay?
So you see that they were willing to forego their privilege, you
know, and their position because they recognized somebody was greater than them.
So that's an interesting question. Is that ענווה? Anavah? To just recognize
hey you might not have a choice which the גמרא Gemara will
be, but you know, there's a difference like the absence of like
being just honest, you know, and acknowledging who's better than you. Is
that is that ענווה? Anavah? I mean for a lot of people
maybe that's a high מדרגה, madreiga, but you know, is that so
we'll see where the גמרא Gemara goes with this. Wait you saying
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל was the first נשיא? Nasi. No, he was
a descendant of הלל, Hillel, הלל Hillel was the first נשיא. Okay,
דאמר de'amar okay.
יונתן בן שאול, Yonatan ben Shaul, יונתן Yonatan דקאמר ליה לדוד dekamar
lei l'Dovid because he said to דוד Dovid ואתה תמלוך על ישראל
ve'atah timloch Yisrael you will be king of Israel ואני אהיה לך
למשנה ve'ano eheyeh lecha lemishneh and I will be your second-hand man
when he was also willing to accept his position. So the second
two stories are quite interesting because they're people that sort of recognize
what's going to happen, recognize people's other people's talent, accepting their position.
Maybe that's it. You know, maybe ענווה Anavah is not not thinking
that you're less than you are, not being falsely modest, not being
dishonest with your own ability, but being honest enough to know that
other people could have greater abilities than you and knowing your knowing
sort of where you are relative to other people. רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל was very modest. Well right. So let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara says ממי, mi'mai, how do you
know that these that these three are so ענווי? anavay? And I
think also Dov's point of how do we want to translate this
as honesty as modesty or humility? How do you know that these
people had ענווה? Anavah? דילמא יונתן בן שאול דחזא דאגדי עלמא בתר
דוד. dilma Yonatan ben Shaul dechaza d'agdi alma batar Dovid.
Maybe יונתן בן שאול Yonatan ben Shaul saw everybody was going after
דוד, Dovid, and you know, he was more perceptive than he was
ענו, anav, you know, better to hitch your wagon to the guy
who's going to be the king than to try to resist it,
right? So, you know, it's just being smart. And the גמרא Gemara,
says similarly,
בני בתירה נמי דחזו להלל דעדיף מינייהו. Bnei Beteira nami dechazu l'Hillel
de'adig minaihu. They saw הלל Hillel was greater than they. So what
does that mean? But still recognizing somebody is better than you could
be a degree of ענווה. Anavah. So if you look at רש"י,
Rashi, רש"י Rashi says דחזו להלל דעדיף מינייהו dechazi l'Hillel de'adig minaihu
second line from the top
והלכות שהיו נשאלות מהם בבית המדרש נעלמות מהם ובושים בדבר. v'halachos she'hayu
nish'alot meihem be'beis hamidrash ne'elamas meihem u'voshim badavar. They were embarrassed, right,
that they would be or ashamed that they would be asked questions
they wouldn't know, that הלל Hillel would be able to answer. So
that's, you know, that's saying like, you know, better sometimes to do
that because it saves you from the embarrassment. You're going to try
to keep yourself in your position and somebody's constantly going to be
showing that you don't belong there, right? So that's not ענווה, Anavah,
that's just protecting yourself. Okay?
So it's not clear from the גמרא, Gemara right, whether whether noting
being aware of who you are maybe that is ענווה Anavah and
maybe here it wasn't because they were doing it for self-protection. Okay?
Or maybe no, maybe ענווה Anavah is going beyond that to actually
being a little bit like a little
is there a sense of a little denying you know totally you
know downplay exactly what your accomplishments are. Is that part of the
concept of ענווה? Anavah? Not clear. But anyway the way רש"י Rashi
reads it the only reason they're not ענווי anavay is because they
were doing it because they had
to.
Nothing was forcing him to say that, so clearly he was being
an ענו *anav*. You don't know about the other two then. אמר
amar, רבי Rebbi *Amar Rebbi*, חביבין יסורין yissurin, *chavivin yissurin*. So now
רבי Rebbi *Rebbi*, now we're back to this story, רבי Rebbi *Rebbi*'s,
well, you know, רבי אלעזר Rebbi Elazar בר רבי Rebbi שמעון *Rebbe
Elazar bar Rabbi Shimon*'s wife turned him down, and now רבי Rebbi
*Rebbi* is saying, "Oh, it must be that יסורין yissurin *yissurin* are
so valuable because that made him greater than me במעשים טובים *b'maasim
tovim*." Now the question is, really like why did he accept that
just because that's what the wife said? You know, okay, that was
the wife's interpretation that יסורין yissurin *yissurin* made him so great. Why
did רבי Rebbi. *Rebbi* necessarily say, "Oh well, if she said it,
it must be true"? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says חביבין יסורין yissurin
*chavivin yissurin*, third line from the top. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says שראה
שהועילו יסורין yissurin של רבי אלעזר Rebbi Elazar שלא שלטה בו רמה
*sherah shehoyilu yissurin she'Rebbe Elazar shelo shalta bo rimmah*. It wasn't what
his wife said. It was the fact that there was direct evidence
that the body was preserved for, you know, between eighteen and twenty-two
years. And even though, so how did he know that was because
of יסורין yissurin *yissurin*? That I don't know, but again, that was
something which made him so exceptional. And then also maybe there's a
certain connection. This was an affliction of the body and the body
was preserved. So the body was afflicted later. Maybe something like that.
Right. Okay. חביבין יסורין yissurin *chavivin yissurin*. So קבלי תלת עשרי שני
*kabbalei tlat esrei shanei*, he accepted upon himself because now it seems
like, you know, the same with רבי Rebbi אלעזר בר רבי שמעון
*Rebbe Elazar bar Rabbi Shimon*, all you have to do is welcome
the יסורין *yissurin* and then they come in, you know. Then he
can marry his wife. So maybe, I don't know about that. But
it's also funny that you just, once you're prepared to welcome it,
somehow God will bring it about. Maybe if you're רבי *Rebbi* or
רבי אלעזר בר רבי שמעון *Rebbe Elazar bar Rabbi Shimon*, that'll work.
So he accepted upon himself thirteen years of יסורין *yissurin*. I don't
know what the meaning of thirteen is. שית בצמירתא *shita b'tzamarta*, six
in צמירתא *tzamarta*, which רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says is some, no, רש"י
Rashi, *Rashi* says it's a urinary infection. Okay, ושבע בצפרנא *v'shiva b'tzaparna*,
and seven in צפרנא *tzaparna*, which רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says is some
type of... Is it some kind of like kidney stones? Oh, maybe
it's kidney stones. And רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, and רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
says this other one is some type of a disease that is
in the mouth. How do they translate these? A mouth disease. Thrush.
Thrush. Okay, whatever. So okay, ואמרי לה *v'amri lei*,
some say שבע בצמירתא ושית בצפרנא *shiva b'tzamarta v'shita b'tzaparna*.
No, it was the reverse. Seven with the urinary infection and six
with this thrush. Okay. אהדורי דבי רבי *ahdurei d'bei Rebbi*,
now we're going to talk about רבי *Rebbi* being having these afflictions.
Thank you so much. Okay, so אהוריירא *ahuroirah*, which was sort of
like רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says it was the guy who watched the
horses. What's that called? The stableman of רבי *Rebbi*'s household. הוי עתירי
משבור מלכא *havyei atiri mi'Shvor Malka*. He was richer than שבור מלכא
*Shvor Malka*, which was the Persian king. תוספות *Tosafot* quotes a מדרש
*Midrash* that says because of all of the dung from the horses,
that was so valuable that he became richer than the king, the
Persian king. Anyway, that's a little parenthetical point. כד הוה רמי כיסא
לחיותא *kad havei rami kisa lechayuta*, when he would throw the fodder
to the animals, הוה אזיל קלא בתלתא מילי *havei azil kala bitlasa
milei*. So they would like their neighing and their sounds would be
heard from three מילי *milei*, like, you know, three kilometers. I think
a מיל *mil* is about a kilometer. Yeah, three kilometers. Okay, so
probably that's why it tied into he was rich. These were such
huge powerful animals. Okay, so when they ate, you could hear it
for three kilometers. הוה מכווין *havei mechavein*, so he intentionally timed it,
דרמי בהיא שעתא דעייל רבי לבית הכסא *d'rami b'hi sha'ata d'ayeil Rabbi
l'veit hakeisei*, that he gave them their fodder at the time when
רבי *Rebbi* had to go relieve himself. Because as we're going to
see, he wanted it to cover up the sound of רבי *Rebbi*.
Okay, so דאפילו הכי *d'afilu hachi*, and even so, מעבר ליה קליה
לקליה דרבי *ma'avar lei kalyei l'kalyei d'Rebbi*, the sound of רבי *Rebbi*
and, you know, when he was relieving himself, overpowered the sound of
the horses. ושמעו להו נחותי ימא *v'sham'u lehu nchutei yama*, and even
the sailors could hear it. Okay, when he was screaming out in
pain. דאפילו הכי *d'afilu hachi*, now no matter, even though רבי *Rebbi*'s
pain was so great, יסורי דרבי אלעזר yissurei d'Rebbi Elazar, בר רבי
שמעון עדיפי מדרבי *yissurei d'Rebbe Elazar bar Rabbi Shimon adifi mi'd'Rebbi*. רבי
אלעזר בר רבי שמעון *Rebbe Elazar bar Rabbi Shimon*'s like a competition.
You know, יסורין *yissurin* was greater than רבי *Rebbi*'s. דאילו רבי אלעזר
בר רבי שמעון מאהבה me'ahava. באו ומאהבה אזלו *d'ilei Rebbe Elazar bar
Rabbi Shimon me'ahava bo u'me'ahava ozlu*. They came from love and they
left from love. Right, now it's not exactly he doesn't love, they
came because he felt guilty about what he had done but nevertheless
we'll sort of see the story. It was something that he, you
know, out of a, let's say, of a religious motivation. And they
left out of love because, you know, he asked them to leave
when he had to go learn in the בית מדרש Beis Medrash,
*Beit Midrash*. Okay, so it was all very clearly like religiously motivated.
ואילו דרבי עדי מעשה באו ועדי מעשה אזלו *v'ilu d'Rebbi adai masei
bo v'adai masei
ozlu*. They came because of his actions and they left because of
his actions. We'll see what that means. Now you might think the
actions were that he welcomed them because he got turned down by
the wife. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now is actually going
to tell a different story, which is not so much that he
welcomed them. Okay, and let's see the different story. עדי מעשה באו
מאי היא *adai masei bo mai hi*, what's the story that they
came through his actions? דהוא עגלא דהוה קממטו ליה לשחיטה *d'hu egla
d'havei kamamtilei l'shchita*, famous
story. There's a certain calf that they were bringing to שחיטה *shchita*.
אזל תליא לרישיה בכנפי דרבי *azal talya l'reishei b'chnafei d'Rebbe*, and it
went and it ran away, it got away from the שוחט *shochet*,
and it hid in the skirts of רבי *Rebbi*'s cloak. וקא בכי
and it was crying and אמר ליה זיל לכך נוצרת. amar lei
zil lekach notzarta. He didn't show any compassion, he just says go,
this is why you were created to be food, okay? So he
didn't show any compassion. It's not even saying that he shouldn't have
that he shouldn't have in the end that the calf shouldn't have
been שחט. shecht. It's just saying like where's a little compassion here?
Show a little, you know, feel for the animal. So אמרי, amrei,
they said up in heaven, הואיל ולא קמרחם ho'il velo kamracham since
he is not showing compassion, ליתו עליה יסורין, leisu alei yissurin, let
him be afflicted with יסורין, let him, you know, feel what, you
know, pain means and then he'll be able to empathize with other
people's pain. How long did the יסורין last before? I don't know.
ואיידי מעשה אזלו ve'aidei ma'aseh azlu and they left as a result
of an action. יומא חד, yoma chad, one day, הוה קא כנשא
אמתיה דרבי
ביתא, havei ka kansha amtei d'Rebbi beisa, Rebbi's maidservant was like sweeping
the house. הוה שדיא בני כרכשתא וקא כנשא להו, havei shadya benei
karkushta veka kansha lehu,
so there was these weasels, these little baby weasels and she was
like sweeping them away. אמר לה, amar lah, and Rebbi said to
her, שבקינהו, shabkinhu, leave them alone. כתיב ורחמיו על כל מעשיו, ksiv
verachamov al kol ma'asov,
God's compassion is on all of God's creatures. So he showed compassion
on these poor little weasels which one would guess are a lot
less cute than a baby calf. Anyway, אמרי, amrei, and they see,
no depends on your weasels. Anyway, אמרי, amrei,
he learned. Well, not that he actually reflected on the calf story,
he had changed. He had become more compassionate, more sympathetic.
So אמרי, amrei, they said up in heaven, הואיל ומרחם, ho'il umracham,
since he has compassion, נרחם עליה, neracham alei, let us have compassion
on him. Now I don't understand so the יסורין left. I don't
understand, I understand why we're saying that he's not as merit as
יסורין because they came as a punishment rather than something that he
brought upon he welcomed upon himself through religious type of religious motivation.
But I'm not understanding why the fact that they left through an
action as opposed to Rebbi Eliezer they left out of love. Why
isn't it תפסה tafsah for Rebbi that he actually was had changed
and had done a positive action, you know, how is that different
than the leaving out of love, you know, of Rebbi Eliezer Rebbi
Shimon? I'm not exactly certain. Maybe Rebbi Eliezer Rebbi Shimon saw these
more as divine and therefore, you know, related to them more religiously.
Whereas Rebbi wasn't relating to them at least according to this version
of the story as a type you know in a religious context,
he just was sick and he just now happened to have compassion.
So he wasn't sort of treating the whole experience in the same
religious way in which Rebbi Eliezer Rebbi Shimon was. ומרחם ואהבה... umeracham
ve'ahava... right? So I mean there's that connection. Yeah he was ומרחם
umeracham on these things. Right, but the גמרא Gemara is contrasting it.
It says by Rebbi it wasn't as great because they left איידי
דמעשה aidei d'ma'aseh whereas Rebbi Eliezer Rebbi Shimon's left איידי דאהבה, aidei
d'ahava, you know, מאהבה. So yeah but it's an interesting point, Rebbi's
act was an act of אהבה ahava so that's an interesting point.
Okay, okay,
now still with Rebbi Eliezer Rebbi Shimon. כולהו שני יסורי דרבי אלעזר,
kulhu sheinei yissurei d'Rebbi Elazar,
now before we said that when Rebbi Eliezer Rebbi Shimon was dead
and in the attic, you know if you remember before it said
nobody what did it say before? No wild animals were in the
in that town. Now we're going to say when Rebbi Eliezer Rebbi
Shimon was suffering as a result of יסורין the good things that
happened and maybe this ties into the גמרא Gemara that says the
יסורין were מעשים טובים, ma'asim tovim, you know because somehow because he
was suffering that brought goodness to the people around him. Maybe you
know again now this is an idea of theology that we don't
we try to you know sort of bracket a little because it
seems a little bit too Christian, but you know it's not like
the Christians didn't get it from anywhere or that there wasn't some
sort of parallel trend. Okay, the idea that somebody's suffering, you know,
can actually be מכפר mechaper for other people, okay, or you know
bring good to other people. So anyway it says,
where was I? כולהו שני, kulhu sheinei, all the years of יסורי
דרבי אלעזר, as all the years that Rebbi Elazar was in was
feeling with his afflictions, לא שכיב איניש בלא זימניה, lo shachiv inish
belo zimnei, nobody died before their right time. כולהו שני יסורי דרבי,
kulhu sheinei yissurei d'Rebbi, all the years of the affliction of Rebbi,
לא אצטריך עלמא למטרא, lo itzterich alma lemitra, the people did not
need rain. Now it's interesting because that actually would seem you know
going back to the גמרא Gemara that his יסורין were a little
bit mixed, right? The lack of water doesn't seem like a blessing.
Now it is a blessing if you don't need rain if the
ground is irrigated itself naturally or whatever, okay, but it is a
little bit of a mixed experience. It's not as an obvious positive.
Okay, now why is not needing rain a good thing? I mean
why you know? Because rain even though you need rain, rain isn't
always so wonderful as you know. You know it's raining outside it's
a yucky day, you slip. דאמר רבה בר בר שילא, d'amar Rabbah
bar bar Shila, קשי יומא דמטרא כיומא דדינא, kashi yoma demitra k'yoma
dedina, the day of rain is as difficult as a day of
judgment. Meaning it's really ironic, you know, it's like you need the
rain, maybe the world needs judgment, but it doesn't mean it's always
so pleasant when it happens. ואמר אמימר, ve'amar Amemar,
אי לאו צריכא לעלמא, ei lav tzricha le'alma, if rain weren't needed
to keep the world going, בעו רבנן רחמי עליה ומבטלי ליה, ba'u
rabbanan rachamei alei umvatlei lei, they would just cut out the rain.
Like who likes a rainy day, you know? So okay, אפילו הכי,
afilu hachi, so that was the blessing was that there you didn't
need rain and it didn't rain. But I mean again think about
the whole story about אליהו, Eliyahu, right? The whole curse was that
it wasn't raining. So again it's a little bit of a tinged
type of a blessing. It didn't rain but there was also no
drought. I know, there there was a drought. I understand that. It's
still okay. So now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says like this: אפילו
הכי *afilu hachi*, and even though it didn't rain, just to show
you how much rain wasn't needed, כי הוי עקרי פוגלא ממשרא דא
*ki havei akri pugla mi mishra da*, when you would pull out
a radish from where it was in the ground, from its hole
in the ground, הוה קאי בירי מלא מיא *hava kai birei mala
maya*, it would leave behind a hole, a cavity filled with water.
The ground itself was so moist, was so, you know, filled with
water. איקלע רבי לאתריה דרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון *ikala Rebbi le'atreih de'Rabbi
Elazar berabi Shimon*. Now, moving on. So those were the ייסורין *yissurin*.
Now רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi Elazar berabbi Shimon, *Rabbi Elazar berabi
Shimon*, back to the chronology, that רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi Elazar
berabbi Shimon *Rabbi Elazar berabi Shimon* is dead, Rebbi, his wife turns
down Rebbi, we had a whole discussion of comparing them in מעשים
טובים ma'asim tovim, *ma'asim tovim* and in תורה Torah *Torah* and in
they also both suffered ייסורין *yissurin*, etc. Now, back to the story
though. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi Elazar berabbi Shimon *Rabbi Elazar berabi
Shimon* is dead. So now Rebbi comes to the to the village
of רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון *Rabbi Elazar berabi Shimon*. אמר Amar, להו
*amar lehu* and he said, יש לו בן לאותו צדיק tzaddik *yesh
lo ben le'oto tzadik*? Does that righteous person, did he leave behind
a son? אמרו ליה Amru lei, *amru leih* יש לו בן *yesh
lo ben*. Yes, he does have a son. But the son is
a little bit gone off the דרך derech. *derech*. וכל זונה שנשכרת
בשנים *ve'kol zona sheniskeret beshnayim*, any prostitute that would rent herself out
for like two, you know, whatever, two dollars or whatever the two
is, שוכרתו בשמונה *socharto bishmona*, hires him, you know, for eight, meaning
so he basically is a male prostitute. Okay, and he's so beautiful.
Okay, we're getting back to the beauty, although the beauty was with
רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan. *Rabbi Yochanan* and it wasn't with רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון *Rabbi Elazar berabi Shimon*, but whatever it is, okay, he's
so beautiful that the prostitutes hire him out.
אזל *azal*, so what is Rebbi going to do now? He wants
to he wants to help this son of this great צדיק *tzadik*.
Also raises questions, right, here he was this tremendous צדיק *tzadik*, how
did this happen to his son? So anyway, אתייה אסמכיה ברבי *atyei
asmechei beRebbi*. So the first thing he did was he gave him
סמיכה semicha *semicha*. Okay, which is pretty amazing, which is like, you
know, which is like give him סמיכה *semicha* and then he'll have
to live up
to
it. All right. ואשלמיה לרבי שמעון בן איסי בן לקוניא *ve'ashlamei leRabbi
Shimon ben Isi ben
Lekunya*, אחות דאמיה *achot de'imei*, his mother's... actually אחוה דאמיה *achva de'imei*,
his mother's brother, his uncle. I think it was probably his uncle,
means means רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון *Rabbi Elazar berabi Shimon*'s uncle. I'm
guessing because I don't think it was Rebbi's uncle. But anyway, who
do they say here whose uncle that was? Which what does the
translation say? Does it say it was Rebbi or רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון *Rabbi Elazar berabi Shimon*'s? Okay, whatever. Anyway, כל יומא הוה אמר
*kol yoma
hava amar*, לקריתיי אנא אזיל *le'kiryati ana azil*. Every day this son
of רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון *Rabbi Elazar berabi Shimon* would say, what,
I should go to my lessons?
So I don't want to go to my lessons, I want to,
you know, I want to go home. So אמרו ליה *amru leih*
they said to him, חכים עבדו יתך *chakim avdu yach*, how can
you think to avoid your lessons? They they they announced that you
are a חכם *chacham*, right? When they made you when they gave
you סמיכה *semicha*. וגולתא דדהבא פרסו עלך *ve'gulta de'dahava parsu alach*, and
they put upon you a golden cloak. It's very interesting, you actually
get an image of like this investiture ceremony that they would do
when they gave somebody סמיכה *semicha*. ורבי קרו לך *veRebbi karu lach*,
and they announced that you were a רבי *Rebbi*. This is what
they did when they gave you סמיכה *semicha*. ואת אמרת לקריתיי אנא
אזיל *ve'at amart le'kiryati ana azil* and you say... I'm sorry, I
meant that wrong. לקריתיי *le'kiryati* is not my reading, my lessons, it's
לקריתיי *le'kiryati*, my sitting. Okay, he used to say לקריתיי אנא אזיל
*le'kiryati ana azil*, I want to go back to my village. Okay,
and he said, how can you do that? They called you a
חכם *chacham*, they put this gold cloak on you, they called you
a רבי *Rebbi*, ואת אמרת לקריתיי אנא אזיל *ve'at amart le'kiryati ana
azil* and you want to just go back to your village? You
don't want to stay and do your lessons? אמר להו *amar lehu*
מומי *mumi*, it's an oath, עזובא דא *azova da*,
I'm abandoning this desire, I'll stick here, I'll I'll you know, I'll
focus, I'll do my lessons. כי גדל *ki gadal*, now when he
grew up, אתא יתיב במתיבתא דרבי *ata yativ be'mesivta de'Rebbi*. So they
sent him to Rebbi's מתיבתא *mesivta*. שמעיה לקליה *shamei le'kaleh* so Rebbi
heard the voice, some student was asking a question or talking to
a fellow student, ואמר *ve'amar*, הקלא דמי לקלא דרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון
*ha'kala damei le'kala de'Rabbi Elazar berabi Shimon*. I know I know that
voice, that voice sounds like רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון *Rabbi Elazar berabi
Shimon*. אמרו ליה *amru leih* ברה הוא *breih hu*, it's his son.
So now look what happened, his son actually became a תלמיד חכם
talmid chacham *talmid chacham* after he had been after he had been
given סמיכה *semicha*. So קרי עליה *kari aleih*, so Rebbi called on
him about him, פרי צדיק עץ חיים *pri tzadik etz chayim*, the
fruit of the righteous is a tree of life, ולוקח נפשות חכם
*ve'lokeach nefashot chacham*, and one who takes the souls, who you know
who cultivates the souls, you know, is a wise person. פרי צדיק
עץ חיים *pri tzadik etz chayim* זה רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi, ברבי
אלעזר *zeh Rabbi Yosi berabi Elazar*. That's רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi ברבי
אלעזר *Rabbi Yosi berabi Elazar*, the son of רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון
*Rabbi Elazar berabi Shimon*. That's the פרי צדיק *pri tzadik*. ולוקח נפשות
חכם *ve'lokeach nefashot chacham*. Oh, the son of...
I'm sorry, זה רבי יוסי *zeh
Rabbi Yosi*. רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* is the son's name. Did we
say that until now, that his son's name was רבי יוסי *Rabbi
Yosi*? I don't know, but his son's name was רבי יוסי *Rabbi
Yosi*. So זה רבי יוסי *zeh Rabbi Yosi*, this is רבי יוסי
*Rabbi Yosi*, the one who now is the son who is in
Rebbi's שיעור *shiur*, who had been given סמיכה *semicha*, the son of
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון *Rabbi Elazar berabi Shimon*. That's the פרי צדיק
*pri tzadik*. ולוקח נפשות חכם *ve'lokeach nefashot chacham*. ולוקח נפשות חכם, the
one who takes the souls is wise, and זה רב שמעון בן
איסי בן לקוניא, Zeh Reb Shimon ben Isi ben Lekunya, that's the
one who took his soul under his wings, you know, and taught
him and nurtured him until he could, and he was very wise
and look at how he, you know, and of course רבי was
the one who orchestrated the whole thing. Okay, so רבי helped save
the son of רב אלעזר בר רב
שמעון. Reb Elazar bar Reb Shimon. כי נח נפשיה, Ki nach nafshieh,
now when רבי יוסי, the son of רב אלעזר בר רב שמעון
Reb Elazar bar Reb Shimon died, so אמטויה למערתא דאבוה, amtuia lemarta
de'avuah, they brought him to the cave of his father. Remember, they
brought his father to רב שמעון בר יוחאי's Reb Shimon bar Yochai
cave, right?
And initially the snake wouldn't let them in, and then they said,
"Let the son come to the father," and he came in. So
now it's when they bring רבי יוסי to his father's—to the family's
cave here where רב שמעון בר יוחאי Reb Shimon bar Yochai and
רב אלעזר בר רב שמעון Reb Elazar bar Reb Shimon are buried.
So דאבוה, de'avuah, הוי הדרא עכנא למערתא, havei hadra achna lemarta, same
story, the serpent was blocking the entrance to the cave. אמרו ליה,
and again רש"י Rashi, says it was the serpent like with the
tail in its mouth. עכנא. Achna. They said to
him, "עכנא עכנא," Achna Achna, snake, serpent,
serpent, פתח פיך ויכנס בן אצל אביו. p'tach pichah veyikanes ben etzel
aviv.
Open your mouth and let the son come into the father, which
is what they said with his father when they brought his father
there. לא פתח להו. Lo p'tach lehu.
He didn't open the mouth; he didn't let them in. כסבורים לומר
שזה גדול מזה. Kesvurim lomar shezeh gadol mizeh. They assumed, "Oh, this
must show that the father was greater than the son." Why? Either
because the father doesn't want to be in the same cave—they're not
equals—or maybe it's also saying because when the same thing happened when
the father died, the snake did open up the mouth, and now
the son is dying and we're trying to bring him in the
cave and the snake didn't open up the mouth. So יצתה בת
קול ואמרה, yatzta bat kol ve'amrah,
a heavenly voice came out and said, לא מפני שזה גדול מזה.
lo mipnei shezeh gadol mizeh. It is not because the father was
greater than the son. אלא זה היה בצער מערה וזה לא היה
בצער מערה. Ella zeh hayah betza'ar me'arah vezeh lo hayah betza'ar me'arah.
And now it's going back, David, to your point, which we didn't
mention at all yesterday. The father, רב אלעזר בר רב שמעון, Reb
Elazar bar Reb Shimon, was in the cave, the רב שמעון בר
יוחאי Reb Shimon bar Yochai cave story. So the father had suffered
all those years of deprivation in the cave—everyone knows the רב שמעון
בר יוחאי Reb Shimon bar Yochai story about the cave—and therefore maybe
he was more—the cave was more prepared to accept him. You know,
I don't know if this is the same cave, but the point
obviously is there's a cave going on here. So maybe he wasn't
greater in תורה Torah knowledge or he wasn't whatever, but he had
gone through this suffering in this experience, so that's why the cave
was more prepared to accept it. And they were in the cave
together. And oh right, and רב שמעון Reb Shimon and רב אלעזר
Reb Elazar were in the cave together, and now in death here
they're in the cave together. Right, and David made an interesting point
before the class; it was also ironic because רב שמעון's Reb Shimon
running away to the cave was because he was disparaging of the
Roman government, and then his son רב אלעזר בר רב שמעון Reb
Elazar bar Reb Shimon was made a magistrate by the Roman government
and had to sort of be at their service, right? And also
that sort of מדת הדין midat hadin approach that we know when
they came out of the cave was also something you sort of
see there. Anyway, so the son didn't get into the cave, and
it sounds like that's the end of the story—that they had to
bury him somewhere else. Okay, now we go on to another story.
איקלע רבי לאתריה דרבי טרפון. Iklah Rebbi le'atreih deRebbi Tarfon. Now רבי
dropped into the village of רבי טרפון Rebbi Tarfon who had passed
away. אמר להו יש בן לאותו צדיק Amar lehu: Yesh ben le'oto
tzaddik? And he said a similar thing: "Does that righteous man, did
he leave behind a son?" שהיה מקפח את בניו, shehayah mekapeach et
banav, because what רבי טרפון Rebbi Tarfon used to say, whatever, you
know, the famous line of רבי טרפון Rebbi Tarfon is: אקפח את
בני, akpeach et banai, like, "I will, you know,
best my children." It's a question exactly what that word means. It
could very mean almost like, "Let me bury my children if the
following isn't true." How do they translate אקפח? akpeach? רש"י Rashi has
a couple different meanings to it. What do they say? They just
say, "death is burial," "he cut down," "that is burial." Yeah, "let
my—I, you know, on the life of my kids, this is true,
I should bury my kids if this isn't true." So now רבי
wanted to know—it's interesting he calls him a צדיק—but he wants to
know what happened to his kids. Okay, so יש—you know, did he
leave behind any kids or sons? אמרו לו בן אין לו. Very
interesting. No, there are no surviving sons. So that itself sort of
hangs there. He always said, "Let me bury my sons," or whatever,
he did not leave any surviving sons. בן בת יש לו. Ben
bat yesh lo. He did leave a grandson. Okay, because his daughters
survived, his sons didn't, and obviously רבי's only interested in the boys,
so we're moving on, so there's no living sons, but there are
grandsons, sons of a daughter. Okay, בן בת יש לו. Ben bat
yesh lo. And the same story, but he's off the דרך. derech.
וכל זונה שנשכרת בשנים שוכרתו בשמונה. Vechol zonah sheniskeret bishnayim socherato bishmonah.
Okay, any prostitute that rents herself out for two will rent him
for eight. So he's also off the דרך. derech, אייתוהו לקמיה. Aituhu
lekameih. They brought him in front of רבי. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
רבי said to him, אי הדרת בך, Ei hadrat bach, if you
do תשובה, teshuvah, יהבינא לך ברתי. yehavina lach barti. I will give
you my daughter. It's interesting why by רב אלעזר בר רב שמעון
Reb Elazar bar Reb Shimon did he do one approach, just giving
him סמיכה right away, and here he had to like, you know,
seduce him or tempt him with marrying—with offering his daughter. It also
wants to echo—right, it's also the echoes of—exactly,
exactly, it's exactly echoing right, the ריש לקיש Reish Lakish and the
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan, If you do תשובה, teshuvah, I'll give you
my sister. If you do תשובה, teshuvah, I'll give you my daughter.
הדר ביה. Hadar bieh. So he did תשובה. teshuvah. איכא דאמרי Ika
de'amri איכא דאמרי נסבה וגרשה, Ika d'amri nasbah vegeirshah, some say he
married her and then divorced her. איכא דאמרי לא נסבה כלל, Ika
d'amri lo nasbah klal, he even refused to marry her. Why? כדי
שלא יאמרו בשביל זה חזר זה, Kedai shelo yomru bishvil zeh chazar
zeh, so they shouldn't say is that he did it just in
order that he could marry the daughter. Of course it's funny, so
then why so so did it did he do it because of
that? But I mean in the end once he had done the
process that initially motivated him, but once he had become a תלמיד
חכם talmid chacham and you know and done תשובה, teshuva, then he
realized that he should not go through with it, right? I mean
if it really wasn't for that then why you know then why
did Rebbi have to offer it? But obviously by the end he
didn't want it to be about that. It's also clear why he
married her and then divorced her, right? So what, so Rebbi could
say he kept the promise, you know maybe I don't know, anyway
it's not so nice to her. Okay, anyway. Okay, למה ליה כולי
האי, Lama lei kulei hai, now why did Rebbi have to go
to all this effort to make sure that the sons of these
righteous people were on the right דרך, derech, right? למה ליה כולי
האי, Lama lei kulei hai, דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב d'amar Rav
Yehuda amar Rav ואמרי לה אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי
יוחנן v'amrei lei amar Rebbe Chiya bar Abba amar Rebbe Yochanan ואמרי
לה אמר שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן, v'amrei lei amar Shmuel
bar Nachmani amar Rebbe Yonatan, כל המלמד את בן חבירו תורה, kol
hamelamed et ben chaveiro torah,
whoever you know teaches his friend's son Torah זוכה ויושב בישיבה של
מעלה, zoche v'yoshev b'yeshiva shel maalah, will ultimately will sit up in
the heavenly ישיבה yeshiva שנאמר shenemar Academy אם תשיב אשיבך לפני, im
tashiv ashivacha lefanai, אם תשוב im tashuv
if the people will do תשובה teshuva God says to ירמיהו הנביא
Yirmiyahu Hanavi ואשיבך לפני תעמוד, v'ashivacha lefanai taamod, then you will stand
before me. So you know up here up here in heaven and
there's obviously I think an echo of תשוב, tashuv, ישיבה, yeshiva, יושב,
yoshev, ישיבה, yeshiva, תשובה, teshuva,
אשיבך ashivacha etc. Okay, so the whole word ישיבה. yeshiva. So if
you get people to do תשובה, teshuva, you will stand in front
of me. Now I don't know how that's exactly תשובה teshuva is
exactly Torah and getting people in general is בן חבירו, ben chaveiro,
but anyway the גמרא Gemara understands that you know if this is
your friend and you care about your friend, I mean you should
care about the whole world but you know you can't start with
the whole world so then you should also care about what happens
you know to your colleague's children as well. Like a teacher's like
your father. Oh well yes that's certainly that's certainly another echo, but
I don't know if that's exactly here about the יושב בישיבה של
מעלה. yoshev b'yeshiva shel maalah. וכל המלמד את בן עם הארץ תורה,
vechol hamelamed et ben am haaretz torah, anybody who teaches the son
of an ignoramus Torah of a you know אפילו הקדוש ברוך הוא
גוזר גזירה מבטלה, afilu Hakadosh Baruch Hu gozer gezeira mevatla, I don't
know if that's ignoramus is the right term, but anyway you know
an unlearned person אפילו הקדוש ברוך הוא גוזר גזירה מבטלה. afilu Hakadosh
Baruch Hu gozer gezeira mevatla. That is such a high מדרגה madreiga
that you actually are like reversing the course of things. I mean
one is like taking care of those closest to you, right? You
know it's sort of like you know you look after your friend
dies he leaves a child you want to make sure he gets
a good education, you know you look after your friend and you
know your friend's family and those closest to you. This is you
know it's not your friend and it's actually you're reversing like almost
the natural course of things, right? So in that case
even if הקדוש ברוך הוא גוזר גזירה מבטלה בשבילו, Hakadosh Baruch Hu
gozer gezeira mevatla bishvilo, God will annul the decree for your behalf.
You managed to change the course of nature so now you know
God will change the course of nature for your behalf. שנאמר shenemar
ואם תוציא יקר מזולל, v'im totzi yakar mizolel, if you can bring
out something beautiful from something degraded כפי תהיה, k'pi tihyeh, you will
be like my mouth. What you say will you know will be
done. אמר רבי פרנך אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rebbe Parnach amar Rebbe
Yochanan, said Reb Parnach in the name of Rebbe Yochanan כל שהוא
תלמיד חכם ובנו תלמיד חכם ובן בנו תלמיד חכם, kol shehu talmid
chacham u'beno talmid chacham u'ben beno talmid chacham, if you're able now
because we talked about you know making sure that the Torah passes
down to the children and these תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim their sons
are on the right דרך, so if you're תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
and your son is and your grandson is שוב אין תורה פוסקת
מזרעו לעולם, shuv ein torah poseket mizaro l'olam, you can be confident
that the Torah will stay in your family forever. You've now sort
of you know made it such a you've deeply entrenched it into
the ethos of your family. Okay שנאמר shenemar as the verse says
ואני זאת בריתי אותם אמר השם va'ani zot briti otam amar Hashem
לא ימושו מפיך, lo yamushu mipicha, the Torah will not remove from
from your mouth
ומפי זרעך ומפי זרע זרעך umipi zaracha umipi zera zaracha אמר השם
מעתה ועד עולם, amar Hashem meiata v'ad olam, says God from here
and forever. מאי אמר השם, mai amar Hashem, why is אמר השם
amar Hashem you know interrupting that פסוק? pasuk? The whole thing was
אמר השם, amar Hashem, why did it sort of break in the
middle of the פסוק? pasuk? אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא אני ערב לך
בדבר זה, amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu ani areiv lach b'davar zeh, I
will be the guarantor. Once you've achieved מפיך ומפי זרעך וזרע זרעך,
mipicha umipi zaracha v'zera zaracha, then I השם Hashem am going to
promise you you know מעתה ועד עולם. meiata v'ad olam. Now it's
interesting though that the מהרש"א, Maharsha, you know it's a question of
like so what, you don't have to work for it, like you
know what about that whole line in פרקי אבות Pirkei Avot אין
התורה ירושה לך, ein hatorah yerusha lach,
right? So the מהרש"א Maharsha says that it doesn't mean that you
don't have to work for it, but God is going to sort
of you know like a guarantor doesn't mean you don't have to
pay back the loan. Okay, you have to pay back the loan
but God is just going to make sure that it happens. So
you know you still have to work even if you know you
come from a family of Torah, you still have to work for
it but God is going to be there to help and to
make sure that it happens. קביעות. kveiut. So
מאי מעתה ועד עולם? mai meiata v'ad olam? אמר רבי ירמיה מכאן
ואילך תורה מחזרת על אכסניא שלה. amar Rebbe Yirmiyah mikan v'eilach torah
mechazeret al achsanya shela. From that point on the Torah goes back
to its its home, you know to אכסניא achsanya its lodging. So
even if you know maybe things like stray a little bit or
whatever, ultimately you've set you know your family as a house of
the lodging of Torah through all these generations. Ultimately, you know, the
תורה Torah will find its way back, you know, there. So, the
מהרש''א Maharsha also points out the phrase מחזרת mechazeret and not חוזרת.
chozeret. חוזרת chozeret would just mean return, but מחזרת, mechazeret, you know,
sometimes the גמרא Gemara. talks about like being מחזרת mechazeret as somebody
who's like searching after something. So, he again ties it into this
idea that it's not to say it doesn't require effort. But if
you put forth the effort, then, you know, there's the truth, the
fact that you're coming from this type of a family, you know,
that'll help, you know, help, you know, help, you know, push you
along the way. It doesn't just happen automatically, but it helps push
you along the way. רב יוסף יתיב ארבעין תעניתא. Rav Yosef yasiv
arbain tanisa. רב יוסף Rav Yosef sat for forty fasts in order
to reach a high level. ואקריוה, ve'akru'ei lei, and
they read to him in a, in his dream, in his dream
he saw the, he heard or he saw the following פסוק pasuk
being read, לא ימושו מפיך. lo yamushu mipicha. That ah, you've reached
such a high level the תורה Torah now will never leave from
your mouth. יתיב ארבעין תעניתא אחריני, yasiv arbain tanisa achrinei,
he sat another forty fasts. ואקריוה לא ימושו מפיך ומפי זרעך. ve'akru'ei
lo yamushu mipicha umipi zarecha. It
also won't leave your children. Okay. יתיב מאה תעניתא, yasiv me'ah tanisa,
then he did, some say מ, mem, it was another forty. Anyway,
there's another forty or a hundred, maybe a hundred worked to emphasize
like it was a whole higher מדריגה madregah אחריני, achrinei, עשי, asei,
אקריוה, akru'ei,
and now they came and they read to him in his dream,
לא ימושו מפיך ומפי זרעך ומפי זרע זרעך. lo yamushu mipicha umipi
zarecha umipi zera zarecha. Grandchildren. אמר,
then he said, ah, that's what I was going for. מכאן ואילך
לא צריכנא. mikan va'eilach lo tzrichina. I don't have to do any
more fasts. Now that I've got three generations, תורה מחזרת על אכסניא
שלה. Torah mechazeret al achsanya shela. I know the תורה Torah will
remain in my family, it will constantly come back to its like,
to its lodging place. Okay. רבי זירא כי סליק לארץ ישראל, Rav
Zeira ki salik le'eretz yisrael, and when רבי זירא Rav Zeira went
to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, יתיב מאה תעניתא. yasiv me'ah tanisa. Since
we're talking about a hundred fasts to achieve greatness in תורה Torah
or to have תורה Torah. in your family, this is going to
be echoed by the story of a hundred fasts around תורה. Torah
So רבי זירא Rav Zeira when he went to ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, he sat a hundred fasts. Why? דלישתכח גמרא בבלאה מיניה, dilishitkach
gemara bavla minei, that he should forget his Babylonian traditions, his Babylonian
learning, the learning he did in בבל, Bavel, כי היכי דלא נטרדי,
ki heichi dilo nitredei, so it should not distract him. Now what
does that mean? So, you know, I think I remember many many
years ago when I was first here in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
learning in ישיבה, yeshiva, you know, they quoted this גמרא, Gemara right
about, ah, you know, it's like the תורה Torah. of ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, that's the real תורה. Torah Right? רבי זירא Rav Zeira
sat a hundred fasts so he should forget the תורה Torah of
חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz. You know, אוירא דארץ ישראל מחכים. avira d'Eretz
Yisrael machkim. Of course the phrase isn't exactly that. The phrase is
that it shouldn't distract him. How would it distract him? So רש''י
says it would distract him. It actually is a little bit of
a critique of the תורה of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael because in
בבל Bavel they're actually much more, like, analytical, you know, in terms
of the approach. The תלמוד בבלי. Talmud Bavli. The תלמוד ארץ ישראל
Talmud Eretz Yisrael obviously is analytical, but it's not to the same
degree and it's not all of the many different קשיות kashas and,
you know, and, and, you know, and it's
the degree of like challenges and nuances and subtle distinctions and all
of that, it's much, you know, it goes to a one level
of higher degree in the בבלי Bavli than in the, in the
תלמוד ארץ ישראל. Talmud Eretz Yisrael. תלמוד ארץ ישראל Talmud Eretz Yisrael
is also more about just establishing like, it's closer to the original
traditions of the משנה Mishna and the ברייתא Braisa and so on,
and therefore, you know, it's more happy to just deal with פשט
pshat than to deal with like brilliant extrapolations that might not be
the פשט pshat of the text. So if you take a look
at רש''י, right, רש''י says very interesting, נטרדי, nitredei, רש''י says כשעלה
לארץ ישראל ללמוד מפי רבי יוחנן ואמוראי דארץ ישראל לא היו בני
מחלוקת ונוחין זה לזה. k'she'ala le'eretz yisrael lilmod mipi rabbi yochanan ve'amora'ei
d'eretz yisrael lo hayu bnei machlokes venochin zeh lazeh. They were much
more pleasant, they didn't fight as much, כשמן, kishman, כדאמרינן בסנהדרין, k'de'amarin
besanhedrin, ומריחין את התמים בלא קושיות ופירוקין. umarchim es hatamim belo kushas
uveyirukin. They just try to establish the text, don't ask so many
challenges, don't ask so many, now, the question is that could be
a compliment, that could be a little bit of a critique. Of
course, as we learned before, רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan ריש לקיש, Reish
Lakish, ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, and they had a lot of challenges
and so on, so it wasn't that they didn't. But nevertheless, it's
generally is true that the degree of analysis, you know, and what's
the word, there's a word,
dialectic or whatever, you know, is less in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi than
it is in the בבלי. Bavli. There's an interesting מהרש''א Maharsha that
uses this as an opportunity to critique the learning of his day.
I'll just read you the one line from the מהרש''א Maharsha because
he says what do you mean, ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael had good
conceptual learning, you know, and answers and questions. So the מהרש''א Maharsha
just said, yeah, the question is how much are you doing it,
you know, as a type of a, you know, like as castles
in the sky and how much are you really doing it to
get to the truth, right? So he says like this, he says,
it's one type of a question which על ידי פלפולים רווחא שמעתתא,
al yedei pilpulim ravcha shmaita, through the back and forth that you
ultimately get to a better meaning. מה שאין כן בני בבל דאפשר
שהיו מפלפלין דוגמת החילוקים שבדור הזה. ma she'ein kein bnei Bavel d'efshar
shehayu mipalpelin dugmas hachilukim shebedor hazeh. It's possible in בבל Bavel they
would ask all this like, you know, all this פלפול pilpul and
שקלא וטריא shakla vetarya like they do nowadays. אשר כל מי אשר
יודע לכוין על צד היותר בפלפול של הבל, פלפול של הבל, הרי
זה משובח. asher kol mi asher yodeia lechaven al tzada yoser b'pilpul
shel hevel, pilpul shel hevel, harei zeh meshubach. If you could, you
know, somebody who could make a better argument even if it's complete
nonsense, right, oh, look at that brilliant argument, nobody cares if it's
true or not, it's just a brilliant argument. argument, okay? וכל אחד
מכוון לפסול דברי חברו vechol echad mechaven lefasel divrei chaveiro and everybody's
just trying to disprove everybody else. Nobody's really trying to get to
פשט pshat or the truth. וקרי להו מחבלים שנוקבים זה לזה בהלכה
ועל ידי כך לא סלקא שמעתתא אליבא דהלכתא ukari lehu mechablim shenokvim
zeh lazeh ba'halacha ve'al yedei kach lo salka shema'teta aliba de'hilchasa etc.
So he actually uses this as an opportunity to critique what he
thought was the sort of purposeless פלפול, pilpul, which was all to
show your prowess without an attempt to really get to the truth.
Okay? Just checking me on the dates. Yeah.
Oh, it was פלפול pilpul so high quality you had to argue
both sides too. Yeah, it was supposed that was the like the
value was being able to like argue
anything. Right, right, exactly. Well, you learn the skill, but then how
do you apply the skill? Right. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Okay, where are we? Okay. So that he wanted
to forget that.
וצם מאה אחריני, v'tzam me'ah achrinei, and then he fasted a hundred
more תעניות taniyot דלא לשכח רבי אלעזר בשיני delo lishkach Rebbi Elazar
bishinei that רבי אלעזר should not die, רבי אלעזר while he was
alive, ונפקי ליה מילי דציבורא venafki lei milei detzibura and then he
would have to take for whatever reason, maybe this was the, I
don't know if this is the רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, I don't
know if the dates work out here, but anyway, but he did
not want to have to deal with then the communal obligations. Does
it say whether this is the רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון that we're
dealing with before? Because the רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון that we were
dealing with before was the one who was the magistrate, so it
would make sense if that was him, but I didn't check if
the dates work out. Anyway, okay. ויתיב מאה אחריני v'yasiv me'ah achrinei
and then another hundred fasts דלא לשלוט ביה נורא דגיהנם delo lishlot
bei nura degehinnom that he should not be affected by the fire
of גיהנם Gehinnom when he dies. Now, of course, what we're going
to see now is if that was effective, it was going to
be effective even when he was still alive. So he wanted to
test if this was working. So יהבו ביה רבנן עינא, yahavu bei
rabanan eina, I'm sorry, I skipped a line. Okay. כל תלתין יומי
kol taltin yomei every thirty days הוה בדיק נפשיה, hava badik nafsheih,
he would check himself to see how good was he doing in
his fire resistant practice. שגר תנורא, shagar tanura, he would light up
the oven, סליק ויתיב בגויה salik veyasiv begoaveih and he went and
he sat in it, ולא הוה שלטא ביה נורא velo hava shalta
bei nura and the fire didn't affect him. It was pretty dangerous.
Don't try this at home. What? 100 days?
Exactly. יומא
חד, yoma chad, one day יהבו ביה רבנן עינא, yahavu bei rabanan
eina, one day the rabbis gave him the eye, there's that whole
idea of the עין הרע ayin hara that we came up with
before. Who's this guy? Thinks he can prevent, you know, he's, you
know, he's impervious to fire. ואיחרכו שוקיה ve'itcharchu shokeih and his legs
got burned as a result. Oh my God. וקרו ליה vekaru lei
and they called him קטין katin the short one חריך שקיה charich
shakeih with the burned legs. Maybe he was short because because he
had the burned leg, he couldn't stand up to full height. The
מהרש"א Maharsha says that maybe he was called רב זירא Rav Zeira
because maybe that was a variation of רב זעירא. Rav Zeira. זעירא
Zeira is the Aramaic for short.
Okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, מאי
דכתיב, mai dechtiv, what's meant by the פסוק? pasuk? Here's another famous
גמרא. מי האיש החכם ויבן את זאת, mi ha'ish hachacham veyaven et
zot, who is the wise person who will understand this? ואשר דבר
פי ה' אליו va'asher dibber pi Hashem eilav and that God spoke
to him ויגידה veyagiddah and will tell it, על מה אבדה הארץ,
al mah avdah ha'aretz, for what reason was the land was the
land destroyed? And the end of the פסוק pasuk is על עזבם
את תורתי al ozvam et torati because they abandoned my Torah.
So the גמרא says you might know that from like the readings
that we do, right? In the, you know, during תשעה באב Tisha
B'Av etc. So דבר
זה, davar zeh, this thing, אמרו חכמים ולא פירשוהו, amru chachamim velo
peirashuhu, the rabbis said it but they weren't able to explain it
because מי האיש החכם. mi ha'ish hachacham. So that's the חכמים. chachamim.
אמרו נביאים ולא פירשוהו amru nevi'im velo peirashuhu and the נביאים nevi'im
said it but they couldn't explain it. Why was the land destroyed?
Right? אשר דבר פי ה' אליו asher dibber pi Hashem eilav that
God had spoken to the נביא. navi. Nobody could explain why was
it that the land was destroyed, עד שפירשו הקדוש ברוך הוא בעצמו
ad shepeirasho hakadosh baruch hu be'atzmo until God himself explained it, שנאמר
ויאמר ה' על עזבם את תורתי אשר נתתי לפניהם shenemar vayomer Hashem
al ozvam et torati asher natati lifneihem because they abandoned my Torah
that I gave them. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, amar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav, what does that mean? שלא ברכו בתורה תחילה. shelo barchu
batorah techilah. It's so ironic, God had to explain it, and now,
okay, God said this, what does that mean? We'll explain it. In
the end it's the חכמים chachamim explaining what God said.
Anyway, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, שלא
ברכו בתורה תחילה, shelo barchu batorah techilah, they did not make ברכות
התורה birchot hatorah before they learned it. Now, רש"י says that the
play is on the word אשר נתתי לפניהם asher natati lifneihem because
you make a ברכה bracha before you do a מצוה. mitzvah. So
they didn't do the לפניהם, lifneihem, they didn't do the thing that
comes before the learning. Okay, but then רש"י says that this is
because actually this is very consistent with what the מהרש"א Maharsha said,
although it wasn't clear in the גמרא before, is that they were
just doing it because they loved the learning and not because of
the מצוה. mitzvah. Right? If you look at רש"י, you know, maybe
they just love the intellectual challenge. So רש"י says at the end
of the second line from the top, וכיון דלא מברכי, vekeivan delo
mevarchei, since they didn't make the ברכה, bracha, גליא דעתייהו שאינה מתנה
חשובה להם. galia da'ataihu she'eina matanah chashuvah lahem. Not exactly that, not
exactly what I said. They didn't really treasure it. If you don't
make a ברכה, bracha, your ברכה bracha expresses what a gift that
you think it is. By the way, the other reason that this
is brought in besides the is that the language מפיך ומפי זרעך
וזרע זרעך, mipicha umipi zareacha vezera zareacha, right, is the language of
ברכות התורה, birchot hatorah, right? שלא ימושו התורה מפינו ומפי זרענו וזרע
זרענו, shelo yamushu hatorah mipinu umipi zareinu vezera zareinu, right? No, what's
the language of the ברכות התורה? birchot hatorah? Hold on.
וצאצאינו, v'tza'atza'einu, right, wait, right, right. What's the language language? וצאצאינו וצאצאי
וצאצאי. v'tza'atza'einu v'tza'atza'ei v'tza'atza'ei.
What is it? Hold on.
Right. Yeah. והערב נא ה' אלוקינו דברי תורתך בפינו ופי עמך בית
ישראל, V'ha'arev na Hashem Elokeinu divrei Toras'cha b'pinu u'fi am'cha Beis Yisrael,
בפינו, b'pinu, but that's not, okay, וצאצאינו וצאצאינו וצאצאינו וצאצאי עמך בית
ישראל. Vetze'etza'einu, vetze'etza'einu, vetze'etza'einu, vetze'etza'ei am'cha Beis Yisrael. So it's not exactly
the פיך ופי זרעך, picha pi zarecha, but there's certainly elements of
that, and here we're getting the ברכת התורה. Birchas HaTorah. Okay. אמר
ריש לקיש. Amar Reish Lakish. Okay, we did that. אמר רב חמא.
Amar Rav Chama. מהי דכתיב? Mai d'ichtiv? What's meant, בלב נבון תנוח
חכמה, B'lev navon tanuach chochmah, in the heart of a wise person
wisdom will rest, ובקרב כסילים תיוודע, uv'kerev k'silim tivade'a, and in the
midst of the foolish it will be known. So בלב נבון תנוח
חכמה, B'lev navon tanuach chochmah, זה תלמיד חכם בן תלמיד חכם, zeh
talmid chacham ben talmid chacham, again with this whole idea of, you
know, the Torah going through multiple generations, meaning if you are a
תלמיד חכם talmid chacham, the son of a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham
it rests peacefully in your heart. You don't have to go ahead
and boast your Torah knowledge, you're more confident about it and so
on. That's תנוח. tanuach. ובקרב כסילים תיוודע, Uv'kerev k'silim tivade'a, זה תלמיד
חכם בן עם הארץ, zeh talmid chacham ben am ha'aretz, that also
remember before we talked about somebody who teaches the son of an
עם הארץ am ha'aretz and so on. So if you're able to
do this and you're a תלמיד חכם בן עם הארץ, talmid chacham
ben am ha'aretz, which is a major accomplishment, but it's also something
new for you. You know, it's like new wealth, right? You go
around and it's ostentatious, right? As opposed to, right? So you have
to, you're showing it off, you're talking about your Torah all the
time. So that's תיוודע, tivade'a, you make it very well known what
a big תלמיד חכם talmid chacham you were. Okay. אמר עולא, Amar
Ulla, היינו דאמרי אינשי, hainu d'amri inshi, that's what people say, אסתירא
בגלגינא, astira b'galgina, if you have a coin in a pitcher,
so קיש קיש קריא, kish kish karya, it's always making sound. One
coin. If you fill up something with coins, it doesn't make any
sound. If you have one coin, you're hearing it all the time.
Right? I was trying to remember there's an English expression like this,
isn't there? Right. Yeah. Something about like, you know, if you have
a few coins they make a lot of noise. And
here, yeah, there's some English expression like this that I wasn't able
to remember. Anyway. אמרו ליה רב ירמיה לרבי זירא, Amru lei Rav
Yirmeyah l'Rabbi Zeira, Rav Yirmeyah said to Rabbi Zeira, מהי דכתיב, mai
d'ichtiv, what's meant by the pasuk, קטן וגדול שם הוא, katan v'gadol
sham hu,
the small and
the large person, meaning somebody who's great and not so great, are
both there in, you know, עולם הבא, Olam HaBa, okay, or גיהנום
Gehennom or wherever, you know, in the afterlife, ועבד חופשי מאדוניו, v'eved
chofshi m'adonav, and a slave is free from his master. אטו לא
ידעינן דקטן וגדול שם הוא, Atu lo yad'inan d'katan v'gadol sham hu,
what, I wouldn't know that, that everybody goes to עולם הבא? Olam
HaBa? What's the point? אלא כל המקטין עצמו על דברי תורה בעולם
הזה, Ela kol hamaktin atzmo al divrei Torah b'Olam HaZeh, and this
is going, echoing the humility idea, anybody who makes himself small in
Torah in this world doesn't go showing it off, נעשה גדול לעולם
הבא, na'aseh gadol l'Olam HaBa, will become a great one. That's קטן
וגדול. katan v'gadol. If you're קטן, katan, you become גדול. gadol. וכל
המשים עצמו כעבד על דברי תורה בעולם הזה, V'chol hamasim atzmo k'eved
al divrei Torah b'Olam HaZeh, if you make yourself like a slave,
you enslave yourself to Torah, you completely accept the yoke of Torah
in this world, then עבד eved becomes חופשי מאדוניו, chofshi m'adonav, נעשה
חופשי לעולם הבא, na'aseh chofshi l'Olam HaBa, then you become a true
free person of great status in the world to come. Okay. ריש
לקיש הוה מציין מערתא דרבנן, Reish Lakish havah metzayen me'arta d'rabbanan, Reish
Lakish was labeling the caves of the Rabbis, like he was going
in צפת Tzfat and labeling off all the caves of the Rabbis.
כי מטא למערתא דרבי חייא, Ki m'ta l'me'arta d'Rabbi Chiya, when he
came to the cave of Rabbi Chiya, איעלמא מיניה, i'almah minei, he
couldn't find the cave of Rabbi Chiya. חלש דעתיה, Chalash da'atei, he
became despondent. Again, חלש דעתיה. chalash da'atei. אמר, he said, ריבונו של
עולם, Ribono shel Olam, לא פלפלתי תורה כמותו? lo pilpalti Torah k'moso?
Again, who's greater in Torah. Didn't I, again, the word פלפול, pilpul,
didn't I, wasn't I so, you know, have the great discernment and,
you know, ability to ask questions, analysis and so on, the sharpness?
Wasn't I as great as him? יצאת בת קול ואמרה לו, Yatzas
bas kol v'amrah lo, תורה כמותו פלפלת. Torah k'moso pilpalta. Yes, you
were as brilliant as him, as sharp as him, as analytical as
him, but remember, this is ריש לקיש Reish Lakish from the story
of רבי יוחנן before, but תורה כמותו לא ריבצת. Torah k'moso lo
ribatzta. But what you didn't do is you didn't spread Torah like
him. It's not just what you do in the בית מדרש, right?
It's bringing Torah to the people, similar to the point before about
the מעשים טובים, although here it's about Torah. Now, I'm going to
have to end here because it is such a great story, I
don't want to rush through it, where we're going to demonstrate how
רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya was so powerful to spread Torah and it
isn't just your ability to be a good תלמיד חכם and do
good analysis, so we will pick up with that tomorrow. ריש לקיש.
Reish Lakish.